this program is brought to you by
stanford university please visit us at
stanford.edu all right we were
developing the mathematics of linear
operators
as i've emphasized the mathematics of
quantum mechanics is linear algebra
linear algebra consists of a set of
concepts
beginning with a vector space
the vectors represent the states of a
system in ways that will become clear if
that doesn't ring a bell and doesn't
make sense to you now that's okay
just as long as you understand the
mathematical rules of vector spaces at
this point
the states of a system of course not
what you measure what you measure is
observable quantities
things like momentum things like
other quantities that are available
to detect and to record and to measure
and the measurable quantities are
represented not by vectors in the vector
space
but by linear operators
hermitian linear operators so we need to
develop that concept we started
i don't know how many times we started
but let's just review very very quickly
a linear operator
i won't i won't explain to you again
what linear means
but a linear operator
let me find a piece of
chalk this is not chalk
yeah
a linear operator i will represent by a
capitalized letter and i'm going to put
a little hat over it just to indicate
that it's a that it's a linear
operator it
acts it operates it does something to
vectors
in particular it does something to ket
and gives you new ket vectors i'm going
to call this one c
all right now
that allows us
that together with the idea of the dual
vector space
and the notion of inner product allows
us to define what are called matrix
elements of operators
matrix elements of operators kind of are
numbers they're all numbers
they're a collection of numbers
a number for each pair of states that
you can write down each pair of states
let's say a and b
all right and they're simply defined
let the operator
act
on a
it gives you a state it gives you
another vector
let me put a bracket around it to
indicate
that k has acted on a to give a new
state that i could call c but let me
just leave it this way
and now take the inner product of that
with another vector b
that is usually simplified the notation
for it is usually simplified just to be
k
a
but the way that you read it
is k acts on a to give a new vector
k times a
and then you take the inner product with
b
and the result is called the matrix
element of k i should put some hats over
this shouldn't i
to indicate that it's an operator
this
sometimes just
more briefly called kba
it's called the matrix element of k
between vector b and vector a
and it's a notation
that's
very closely related to matrix nokit
notation
now
remember the idea of a basis of vectors
a basis of vectors is a collection of
vectors
which i can label n
if the dimensionality of the vector
space is whatever it is d for dimension
then a basis has d independent vectors
all of them orthogonal to each other and
all of them of unit length
so just pictorially
a basis
it's hard to draw vectors in a complex
vector space the best i can do is to
draw them in a real vector space
but for example these would be a basis
of vectors in ordinary real
three-dimensional space
there are other bases
another basis for example would be let's
see if we have another color of chalk
another basis
might be tilted relative to this basis
these are intended to be all mutually
orthogonal vectors all of unit length
the blue vectors
uh in three dimensions and these are two
different bases the blue basis and the
black bases
let's pick a basis of vectors
so let's erase the blue basis
and simply enumerate
the basis vectors 1 2 and 3 for example
and that's the collection of cat vectors
n
can we represent red states
boy michael you're on tonight
we could be all home listening to the
president give the last state of the
union address
has everybody decided who they're going
to vote for in the primaries
you haven't
you better know which party you're going
to vote for
anybody who votes for the other party
out of here now
okay um
yeah so given a basis of vectors
we can
tabulate or record all of the
matrix elements of k
between
vectors n and m and that's a table it's
a kind of table a square table of
elements
n by n matrix an n by n matrix
k 1 1 k 1 2 and so forth
let's put k 2 1 down here
and we tabulate them write them all down
it makes a matrix an n cap a
a square matrix
whose size
is
equal to the dimension of the space okay
so those are the matrix elements of k
and they really do describe the entire
uh operator k they describe it in in
some detail
there they uniquely describe it yes
i i mean n and m to be basis vectors
drawn from the same basis
right
n m are basis vectors drawn from the
same basis
all right so this could be
n equals three m equals two and so forth
so since there are how many basis
vectors there are d where d is the
dimension of the space
d basis vectors and therefore d squared
matrix elements n can run from one to d
m can run from one to d
okay now let me remind you about
something else i'll write it over here
about a basis
a basis has the property
that you can expand any vector in it
that you can take any vector whatever
let's call it a
and write it
as a sum over n
of a set of coefficients let's call them
a sub n
times the basis vector n
sum over the basis vectors uh i'll i'll
include the summation signs
so that any vector can be represented in
terms of them that's just a statement
the anal the analog of the statement and
in three dimensions any vector can be
represented in terms of three basis
vectors
okay
again
the
set of coefficients a sub n
is
nothing but
the inner products
of the nth basis vector with a
is equal to a let me call it m let me
call
this is supposed to be an
m so the
particular coefficient a
is just given by the inner product of a
with m that allows us to rewrite
any vector
in the interesting form
sum over n
now let me write down the vector n first
right n first and then after having
written n let me plug in the coefficient
n a
this is a kind of expression that will
occur over and over
where you see an in standing next to an
end like that
summed over
whenever you see that it's just a way of
oops
this should be closed like that
a is a vector
whenever you see an expression
like
n standing next to n
with their noses pointed toward each
other
summed over in
you can always
say
all of this
sort of does nothing it just gives you
back a
so keep that in mind whenever you see a
sum like this within within
you can it's there it's uh it's a real
thing
but
it sort of just can be thought of as
what we thought of as the unit operator
the unit operator on a gives you back a
but if you didn't understand that that's
not important
this is a correct expression
so now
let's go back
to the action
of the linear operator k
on an arbitrary vector let's take k
and apply it
to a
what i want to do
is i want to calculate oh let's let's
come back over here
one way of describing the vectors
is just to describe them symbolically or
abstractly as vectors but another way is
just to give
the coefficients a sub m if i know all
the coefficients a sub m
i know the vector a
in particular if i have a specific basis
picked out the set of coefficients is a
representation of the vector it's a way
of describing the vector
and so there's
an abstract notation for vectors and
there's a more concrete way of
describing them as a collection of
components these are the components of
the vector
now here is an abstract operator
being applied to an abstract vector
i'm interested in working this out in
terms of the components of the vector
the actual numerical components of the
vector so the first thing i might like
to know k times a is a vector i would
like to know its components
its components
are just gotten by taking the inner
product with the basis vectors
so this is the nth component of the
vector k times a or k acting on a
let's work this out
by writing a in terms of components
here's a written in terms of components
like this
so let's plug in
for a
m
a
summed over m
that's the same expression that's
written here
the only difference is here i've used
the index n for the summation variable
here i've used the index m for the
summation variable
and now we can rewrite this
as k
n m
this is the matrix element of k between
the vector between the basis vector m
and the basis vector n
times a sub m
summed over m
so we can reduce
the problem
we can reduce the problem of calculating
the components of k times a
to a set of operations all on components
and matrix elements
this is another way of writing the
matrix k
acting on the column vector a
all right i assume that everybody here
has done a little bit of homework and
learned a little bit of linear algebra
this is simply another way of writing
the matrix k
times the column vector a
to get another column vector
this is a column vector because it's a
vector
whose
components
are labeled by n
so
here's an example
of the application of matrix notation or
matrix construction
to the
idea of a linear operator acting on a
vector
now we can multiply linear operators
together what does it mean to multiply
two linear operators
multiplying two linear operators
let's call one of them what have i
called it l
let's
k times l
k times l if k and l are operators
is another operator which means that it
can operate on a vector a
all it means
is you first act with l on a to get a
new vector l times a
let's say we can write it this way it's
k
acting
or operating on
the vector l
multiplied by a
so l times a gives you a new vector and
then you hit it you hit the whole thing
with k
so whatever l on a does then hit it with
k
that defines the operation k times l
but now there's an interesting question
we can ask
if operators are characterized by matrix
elements
what are the matrix elements of a
product like k times l incidentally as
most of you probably know
k times l is not necessarily the same
thing as l times k
these are operators they're not numbers
one has to check whether you can
change the order of them and in general
you can't
linear operators
are not commutative you can't change the
order necessarily in which in which they
act all right so let's consider the
matrix elements
of
k times l
what does that mean
that means
uh
yeah that means
sandwich the operator k times l between
the basis vectors and an m
all right now here is l times m
let's write that in another way let's
write that by sticking by writing l
times m
is the sum over yet another
index i need a summation index now so
let's call that summation index r
right we take l times m
we take its inner product with r
and then we multiply it by the vector r
again this construction where you see
r's and r's nose to nose like that
it simply means
uh well
it simply gives you back the left hand
side oops there's a missing bar in here
there's a missing
vertical line in there
okay so that's l that's l times m let's
plug it into here and then we can write
that this is equal to
n
k with a little hat on top of it and
then let's substitute this in for l
times m
it's r
r
summed over r
okay now we have a nice construction we
have everything written in terms of
components let's get rid of this
and we can now write that the components
or the matrix elements
in
well let's
let's k times l
the n m
matrix element of it this is the n
m matrix element of k times l what is
that given by it's given by n k r
that's k
n r
times l r m
summed over r
all right again this is simply matrix
multiplication written out in longhand
the matrix
representing kl
is simply the product of the matrices of
k and l that's what this reads
this is longhand notation
for the
matrix product
of the matrix k and l
so multiplying linear operators
is an abstract idea
you simply follow the action of one
operator by another operator or it's a
concrete idea that you can represent by
by matrix multiplication
now i'm not going to go very heavily
into this because i'm going to assume
that everybody knows it
among other things it was discussed
elaborately in the last class on quantum
mechanics which i gave on quantum
information and
entanglement
so i will assume everybody knows how to
relate this to matrix multiplication
next idea the idea of a hermitian
operator mission operators are special
classes of operators
they play the role
in our in
in operator theory of things which are
real real in the sense of real versus
imaginary or real versus complex
let's
let's define hermitian opera first of
all let's spell her mission operators
that's not right
what's that
where
hermite
hermite her mind
is not a bug it's the name of a
mathematician
and her mission
hermite
is a proper noun her mission is an
adjective
her mission operators
what is a hermitian operator
well it stands for something which in
classical mechanics would be a real
quantity a real thing that you can
measure
such as location of a particle the
x-coordinate of a particle the momentum
of a particle the angular momentum all
of those are real quantities real as
opposed to imaginary
all right so a hermitian operator and
i'm going to call her mission operator
by the generic term h
now later on h is going to stand for
hamiltonian for now it just stands for
her mission
so let's not worry about hamiltonians
yet
it just stands for her mission
her mission operators as all operators
have little hats on top of them
her mission operators are defined in the
following way
their matrix elements
are such that if you
interchange the bra vector and the ket
vector
keep the operator the same
then all that happens is it becomes
complex conjugated
if you think about it for a moment
if complex conjugating a the complex
conjugating the ket vector a gives the
bra vector a
and complex conjugating b
gives you the bra vector b
then in order to get a complex conjugate
of the left hand side on the right hand
side you should also have to complex
conjugate h somehow
but h
the hermitian operators are exactly the
ones that you don't have to do anything
to
in order to get this work to work out
let me give you another example
supposing we sandwich a hermitian
operator not between two different
vectors but between the same vector
in other words take a
h
a
where a could be any vector whatever
well according to this equation
it's equal to a
h
a
complex conjugate
interchanging the bra vector and the ket
vector will do nothing if the bra vector
and the ket vector are the same but then
this equation just says
that the left hand side is the same as
the complex conjugate of the right hand
side
and things which are their own complex
conjugates are real
all right so sandwiching a hermitian
operator between the same state on
either side
necessarily gives you something real
incidentally this can be taken to be the
full definition of a hermitian operator
you can derive the top from the bottom
you can derive the top from the bottom i
won't bother doing it but it does follow
so you can take the definition to be any
matrix or any operator which when you
sandwich it between the same state or
the same vector on both sides gives you
something real
it follows from that
that if you interchange the bra and the
ket in a matrix element of h that you
get complex conjugate another way to
write it
h
a b
is the complex conjugate
of hba
in particular it's also true the same
thing is true for basis vectors
so h m n
if m and n stand for basis vectors
is equal to h complex conjugate
n m where i've interchanged n m
right that is the cap
those are called hermitian
operators
say it again
being her mission a
no
it's a complex conjugate of a hermitian
b
a hermitian a is always real
but
the top equation well they either
obviously the second equation follows
from the first just by setting b equal
to a
but it's interesting that the first
equation also follows from the second
i will leave it to you to uh to try to
prove that it's a it's a couple of lines
of
proof and if
if nobody can prove it i'll do it
another time
all right so those those are the
definitions of hermitian operators in
order to understand the significance of
permission operators
obviously they have a kind of reality
property reality again i emphasize
reality in the sense of complex numbers
they have a kind of reality property
but in order to really appreciate their
the significance of them we have to go
to another concept the concept of
eigenvalues
so let's review very quickly i'm
regarding this as quick review a concept
of eigenvalues and eigenvectors
of operators
now in general when an operator acts on
a vector
here's a vector
an operator acts on it it will do
something to that vector one kind of
operator might rotate the vector
another might reflect it about some axis
there are all kinds of linear operators
but in general it will change the
direction of the operator it will take
you from here for example to
there may be special
directions particular directions
which
when you apply the operator for each
operator given an operator there may be
specific directions and there will be
for hermitian operators
if you have a hermitian operator there
will be directions
that if you apply h to the upper the
vectors in those directions it doesn't
change their direction
for example a simple operator
uh that you can think about
would be an operator which takes every
vector in any direction
and stretches it
uh
along an axis
stretches it out along one axis
doubling its length in one direction
keeping its length in the other
direction fixed
so we might have an operator which
takes any vector and doubles the x
component of the vector for example
leaving the y component fixed
then if i take an arbitrary vector
its direction will change exactly as you
see here but if i take a vector along
the x-axis
then its direction doesn't change
right the direction stays the same
those vectors whose direction do not
change
when you apply a certain operator are
called the eigenvectors of that operator
eigen is a the german word for proper
i think proper
is that what eigen means doesn't change
i i was once told it meant proper
yeah
very very little
own okay
good
all right so the eigenvectors of an
operator are the vectors whose direction
don't change but what does happen to
them then
let's suppose
we haven't we have a
operator i'm taking it to be a hermitian
operator now and i find some eigenvector
let me call the eigenvector lambda
what can happen to it if its direction
doesn't change the only thing that can
happen to it is it gets multiplied
by a number
let's call that number lambda
now the first lambda here is just a
notation for indicating a particular
vector
if
we have if we find a vector that when h
applies to it when h attacks it
just multiplies it by the number lambda
we call that vector the eigenvector of h
with eigenvalue lambda
eigenvectors i'll call them e vectors
and e values
the eigenvector lambda
corresponds to the eigenvector
lambda
if h
hitting that eigenvector simply
multiplies it by the number lambda
that's the yes
or operators yeah yeah all linear
operators yes
that is
uh that is true
not all
operators have
eigenvectors all hermitian operators do
all her mission operators and we're
going to state a theorem now
now i'm not going to prove the theorem
the theorem can be found on the internet
version of my last quantum mechanics
class uh on uh
on an entanglement and that sort of
thing the theorem is an elementary
theorem
it has various pieces
theorem number one
all of the eigenvalues of a hermitian
operator are
what
real
okay they are these these are all easy
to prove statements very easy from the
definition
right basically this is uh this alone
that the matrix element of hermitian
operator sandwiched between the same
state
is always real that's sufficient to
prove it i'll let you figure it out so
number one
e values
of hermitian operators h are real
real numbers
okay
second
part of the theorem or second theorem
two
very easy to prove as i said
the eigenvectors
of hermitian operators
for different eigenvalues if i find more
than one eigenvalue
if there is more more than one
eigenvalue let's call it lambda 1 and
lambda 2 and they're not equal to each
other different eigenvalues the
eigenvectors are what
orthogonal
for
lambda 1
not equal
to lambda 2.
in other words for two different
eigenvalues the eigenvectors are
orthogonal this is not true
of general operators it's true of the
hermitian operators
number three
basically number three says there are a
lot of eigenvectors of permission
operators
how many is the maximum there can be
well they're all
mutually perpendi they're for different
eigenvalues they're all mutually
perpendicular to each other
how many mutually perpendicular
vectors can you find in a d-dimensional
vector space
well maximum is d the theorem says
that you can there are always
d there exist
the
mutually orthogonal
no for her missions
not only at most but also at least
permission
her mission matrices have d mutually
orthogonal
eigenvector eigenvectors
if two of the eigenvalues for two
different eigenvectors happen to be the
same number
still you can find orthogonal
eigenvectors associated with them in
that case the two eigenvalues if they
happen to be the same number are called
degenerate
but let's ignore the possibility of
degenerate eigenvalues for the moment
what does this mean this means that the
eigenvectors of hermitian operators form
bases
in other words there's enough of them
they're all perpendicular to each other
you can always choose them to be unit
vectors why is it that you can always
choose them to be unit vectors
how do i know that i can always take an
eigenvector to be of unit length unit
norm unit uh inner product with itself
well if i have an eigenvector and i
multiply it by any number it's still an
eigenvector with the same eigenvalue
in other words if i take twice lambda
here
that 2 just goes straight through
h
on twice lambda is lambda times twice
lambda so if i multiply an eigenvector
by any number
any
uh just ordinary complex number it could
be complex
any complex number it still stays an
eigenvector with the same eigenvalue so
i can always multiply the eigenvectors
by numerical numbers until i get them to
be of unit length
once i have them of unit length and
they're all mutually orthogonal they
form a basis
this is the basic fact two basic facts
about
hermitian operators their eigenvectors
form a basis and their eigenvalues are
all real
any questions until now
okay
yes
whether they exist
say it again
no rotating rotating axis is not our
mission
actually i'll tell you
it's anti-hermitian
we'll come to the definition of that in
a minute
uh
which means if you multiply it by i it
becomes hermitian now you can ask well
if you multiply it by i and it becomes
hermitian that must mean it has a bunch
of imaginary eigenvalues
yes rotation operators do have imaginary
eigenvalues remember we're dealing with
vector spaces over the complex numbers
just an ordinary rotation happens to
have a complex eigenvalue but if i were
thinking about real vector spaces in
real vector spaces rotation of axes does
not have is not hermitian so that's
exactly right
what does her mission become what's the
concept of her mission do we have it
here
yeah what's the comp supposing we're
talking about a real vector space where
all the numbers matrix elements
everything else
are real numbers
what is the mean what is the analog of
hermitian
the analog of hermitian we just ignore
complex conjugation no such operation is
complex or everything is its own complex
conjugate it's symmetric
a h-a-b is equal to h-b-a or h-m-n is
equal to h-n-m
so a special case of hermitian operators
would be symmetric real
things which are symmetric and real
okay
a rotation of coordinates is
anti-symmetric it's an anti-symmetric
matrix so in that sense uh it's not her
it is not her mission
so are you
the vector space the complex vector
space
yes but let's focus on a particular
vector space
and now take a certain particular
hermitian operator in that vector space
okay
the collection of vectors
hermitian operators act on that vector
space give new vectors take that
now if you want a concrete
representation of it then the concrete
representation is in terms of matrices
basically this says that every hermitian
matrix has a complete orthonormal family
of eigenvectors
and it's also simple
yeah in that basis yes in that basis uh
the form of h is very simple
but uh it may be a difficult job to
figure out what that basis is
so i didn't want to i didn't want to
belabor that point right now but you're
right
all right so if you like thinking
concretely really concretely and not
abstractly as i do
then
it's easy to think of operators simply
as matrices
matrices
h11 h12 blah blah blah blah blah h21
dot dot
vectors as column vectors a1 a2 a3
and then acting with a matrix on a
column vector i will assume you know how
to do that gives you a new vector
if
a is an eigenvector
that means
that the matrix when it acts on a
just gives you a number lambda
times the same
times the same vector
if it is an eigenvector
not all like not all vectors will be
eigenvectors most won't
most vectors won't be eigenvectors but
there will be a complete basis of them
if h is hermitian
so if you like thinking concretely just
think in terms of matrix elements
uh
now we're ready to state the postulates
of quantum mechanics
the first postulate we've already stated
the first postulate is that the states
of the system the configurations the uh
the conditions
describing a system at a given instant
of time
are described
by vectors in the vector space
so
states
equal
the collection
of ket vectors
you could use the bra vectors they're in
one to one correspondence but let's
focus on the ked vectors
that's the first postulate for every
state of a quantum mechanical system
there exists a vector
in a uh in a vector space how many
dimensions does the vector space have
that depends on the particular system
if the system is a coin and that's all
and it can be heads or tails then it's a
two dimensional vector space there are
only two orthogonal states two mutually
orthogonal states if it's a die with six
independent states then the
dimensionality of the space is six
real systems typically have a lot more
states than that
and for example a particle moving in
space
could could be located if we look for it
at any position so it would have an
infinite number of states
but for each state there is a
a uh
a ket vector so that can be taken to be
postulate number one now the number of
postulates i'm going to write down is a
little bit more than is absolutely
needed to minimally
accidentize quantum mechanics
but it's uh it's it's nice to write them
all down in a way which
exposes the ideas and not try to be
absolutely minimal
okay
yes
say it again
you don't observe the states of systems
you observe the observables the
observables correspond to the hermitian
operators but we'll come to that
you don't nobody has ever directly
observed the state of a system
you observe the things which can be
observed which are things like position
momentum
electric field magnetic field
things which record measurements on an
apparatus
and they'd never never never give you
enough information to be able to record
the whole state of a system
so uh
you would never call the state a state
of a system an observable
okay
we'll talk about later at some point uh
we'll talk about how you prepare i don't
know if we will that was talked about
a previous quarter
for the moment states of systems are
described by vectors
that's postulate number one
postulate number two is the things which
you observe now observe means you make
measurements of them you could call them
observables you could call them
measurables you could call them the
things that you measure in an experiment
the things that you measure and
experiment we'll call them observables
that's the usual term for them
the observables
correspond we should really write this
not equals but corresponds to
corresponds to the collection of
hermitian operators
the collection of permission operators
every hermitian operator corresponds to
something that you can measure
in principle
not any old operators but the collection
of hermitian operators
number three
third postulate
the values
you're going to do an experiment now and
you're going to observe a particular
observable
that corresponds to a hermitian operator
h
what are the possible results that you
can get of the measurement
you make a measurement of
h whatever h is
and you get a value
the possible values that you can get the
collection of values that you could get
the values
of
the observable h
are
the eigenvalues
of oops of
h
that's the meaning and the significance
for us of eigenvalues that the values of
the quantity that you can
get when you measure it so they have
they're important is the point
uh not only are they important as i said
they are the things that you get in an
experiment
what else
oh and remember
anytime you do an experiment of a
quantity you get a number and it's
always a real number
if i measure the position of something i
don't get a complex number i get a real
number if i measure the x coordinate or
if i measure the angular momentum or i
measure you know whatever electric field
i get a real number so it's important
no these they usually
if you measure the angular momentum
there's no error bark in the imaginary
direction you may have error bars in the
real directions it's a real number
okay therefore
it's important that hermitian operators
have real eigenvalues
after all those are the things you can
measure
furthermore
the states
for
which if you find a system in that state
or create a system with a particular
state
the states
for which
the
observable h
has a definite predictable value
a certain value a value which is not
subject to statistical fluctuations
those states for which the observable h
is let's say is definite
or or certain as opposed to uncertain
are the eigenvectors of h
the eigenvectors of h in other words if
by one means or another
you created an electron
in an eigen state of some observable
such as its position
and then you measure the position
the measurement will always yield every
time the eigenvalue of the appropriate
operator
the position operator
so the eigenvectors are the states in
which
the observable has a definite value and
the value that it has is the
corresponding eigenvalue
any questions
yes
say it again
well
i think it's more proper to say that you
observe the observable and get a
number and the number corresponds to the
eigenvalue i would say that's more
proper terminology and a more proper way
to think
of course once you do that then you know
that the system
was prepared in a particular state and
in that sense you could say you observe
it but
i i think it's a sort of linguistic
misuse to say that you observe
eigenvectors it's better to say you
observe the observable and the result
that you get is one of the eigenvalues
of the observable
and i think that's a more precise
language
all right so let me give you an example
uh
let's uh take an example such as the
spin of an electron
some particular component of the spin of
an electron
if you measure if you prepare an
electron in an arbitrary state how do
you do that you put the electron in the
magnetic field go back to course on
quantum mechanics number one and read
about how you prepare an electron
with its spin along a particular axis
supposing you did that
and then
you measure the spin
along some other axis
then you may get plus or minus you may
get with a certain statistical
probability you will get different
answers
but if you measure the spin along the
axis that you prepared it along then you
will get a definite answer you'll get a
definite answer corresponding to the
spin that you the way that you prepared
it so there are certain states which if
you measure certain quantities
you will always get the same answer
you do a certain experiment on this
an experiment i mean you place it in a
field you do something to it and at the
end of doing something to it you measure
something
sometimes the measurements will give you
statistically ambiguous answers with a
probability distribution depending on
what you measure and depending on what
state it's been put in
other times
if the thing you're measuring
corresponds correctly to the state that
you've created the system with
then you may get definite answers we'll
we'll see some examples
definite means there's no statistical
uncertainty in the value that you get
so there are certain states
for each observable there are certain
states where you will definitely get a
particular answer and you'll always get
the same answer
namely if the system has been prepared
in an eigenvector of a particular
variable and you measure that variable
you'll always just get the eigenvalue
right so that's another
that's the fourth postulate
and the fifth postulate
is what happens if you start with a
state which is not
an eigenvector of the of the quantity of
interest
so in other words supposing instead of
preparing a system
with a state
which happens to be an eigenvector of h
you prepare some other state somehow and
i'll give you examples we'll come to it
but let's state the postulates four and
number five take an arbitrary state of a
system
made god knows how however it was
however the system was originally
created
an electron may be created created by
shooting it out of an accelerator or
something in some particular way we make
the electron in some particular state
and we now measure something or other
about the electron okay we measure the
h-ness of the electron
what can we get we can get answers which
are the various eigenvalues let's call
them lambda 1 dot dot dot lambda n
these are all the possible answers we
could get
the various eigenva eigenvalues
of
lambda
for each of these eigenvalues there is
the eigenvector
we can call it i don't know let's just
call it lambda n
that's the eigenvector that corresponds
to measure definite value
of h with a particular eigenvalue
then
the fifth postulate is about the
probability of getting different answers
lambda one through lambda n
the answer is that the pr or the
postulate is that if you calculate
the component
of the vector a along the axis lambda n
okay think of these lambda n's as a
basis set
their basis set which goes together with
the particular observable
made up out of the eigenvectors of that
observable
take the component of the vector a
along the direction lambda n
that's a complex number in general
in general this is a complex number
could not possibly be a probability
but multiply it by its complex conjugate
so multiply this by its complex
conjugate one way of writing it is take
the absolute value of it and square it
another way of writing it
is to just multiply it by its complex
conjugate sorry lambda n
multiply it by its complex conjugate its
complex conjugate is lambda n times a
you just
invert
bra and ket and that gives you the
complex conjugate so take a no summation
here a
projected on to lambda n
squared or complex conjugated
that gives you the probability
that's the probability
that you measure lambda n
if the system has been prepared in the
state a
so whatever
went in to constructing
a particular configuration of an
electron the particular way that it came
out of the excel the particular uh
magnetic field electric field
various conditions under which the
electron was created define the state a
having defined having created the
electron or whatever the system is
you can then ask what's the probability
that if i measure a particular
observable
h that i get any one of its possible
eigenvalues
the answer is the component of a
along the eigenvector lambda n
times its complex conjugate
this is always a real positive
number okay it's always a real positive
number
and so it can be a probability that
those are the five postulates of quantum
mechanics
there are ways of diminishing the number
of independent postulates but i think
it's better to expose them all
and uh and to say them all
and
not try to be clever
and reduce the number of independent
postulates
okay well now i will give you some
examples soon enough
i was going to talk about incompatible
observables but let's not at this point
let's uh let's do some
examples
the simplest examples correspond to
systems with finite number of states
like the toy the coin toss
or the dice or so forth but i don't want
to begin with that we've done that
we did that repeatedly
in the previous class in quantum
mechanics and quantum
entanglement and so forth which is
basically about these simple systems
with finite numbers of states
let's jump right now to the motion of a
particle on a line
supposing we have our system consists of
a particle in one dimension the particle
can be anywheres on a line
it can move on the line
classically we would just describe this
by a particle with a coordinate x
which could depend on time
quantum mechanically we describe it
completely differently very differently
we describe the states of the particle
by a vector space
what vector space well i'll tell you
right now what vector space the space of
functions of x
remember when we started and i gave you
some examples of vector spaces one of
the examples of vector spaces was
functions of a coordinate complex
functions of a coordinate
psi of x
psi of x corresponds to a vector
in the vector space of complex functions
we can think of it as a vector in a
vector space because we can add
functions and we can multiply them by
numbers
okay we can take inner products
of these vectors let me remind you of
the rule
if i have two functions phi of x
and psi of x
then the inner product between them
is just the integral over the line the x
of
phi star of x
psi of x
wi-fi star of x because phi is the bra
vector
psi is the ket vector so whenever you
have a bra vector it always corresponds
to some complex conjugation
that's the definition of a vector space
for a particle on a line the vector
space can be thought of as
as functions on the axis
well actually it can be a little more
abstract than that
we can think of these functions
differently
we can well no let's not let's not be
more abstract we can come back and be
more abstract later
right
let's think about operators now yes
which
no no inner products are not real
in general what are real is the inner
inner product of a vector with itself
all right so if i were to put psi psi
that would be the inner product of psi
star with psi that would be real
okay
good
all right good question
keep the questions coming because
what's that
say it again
here here and here yeah absolutely just
common
garden variety complex multiplication
right
so that's the inner product now let me
give you an example of some operators we
can check that they are really operators
check that their hermitian
find their eigenvalues
interpret them as observables
and see what their probabilities
correspond to
the first operator
is the observable that corresponds to
the location of the particle along the
axis
and i'm going to tell you what that
operator is and how it acts on
psi of x
we'll call that operator just x x with a
hat on it
and it operates on a vector psi
in terms of functions
what it does
is it takes a function of x
psi of x
and does something to it
it does the simplest possible thing it
multiplies it by x
that's its definition
the operator x hat
acts on the ked vector psi
i should say corresponds to not equals
in such a way that the new vector
if the old vector was represented by psi
of x
the new vector the result of multiplying
it by the operator x hat is just to
multiply the function by x very simple
right
well what would it mean to have an
eigenvector
of the operator x hat
in terms of ordinary functions it would
mean that well what does it mean first
of all in terms of
the abstract notation the abstract
notation
x hat on psi of x
well
no
um
you can't multiply a ket by x you can
only multiply it by the operator x
oh oh oh good good good good yes you
could do that thank you yes that that
would be legitimate
in other words it's the ked vector whose
representation is x times psi of x and
just instead of psi of x yes that's fine
that's good
okay
are there eigenvectors well what would
that mean that would mean that x hat on
psi of x is just equal to some number
oh oh before that let's check that it's
hermitian let's check that it's
hermitian
what does it mean that it's her mission
uh
the
unnecessary and sufficient condition
is that
a
hermitian a is real for all a
that's necessary and sufficient for a
hermitian operator for any for any
vector a
okay let's just check that
all that means
is that psi of x
x hat
psi of x
is real
but what is that
x times psi of x
just corresponds to the vector x psi of
x just corresponds to the function x i
of x taking its inner product
with the bra vector psi of x
means multiplying it by psi star of x
and integrating
this is surely real psi of x times psi
star of x is real
x is real dx is real
this is a real number
all right
whatever psi is this is always real so
it follows that the inner pro that the
uh that the matrix element of x between
equal vectors is always real
that's necessary and sufficient for x to
be a hermitian operator so x is
hermitian
that must mean has a lot of eigenvectors
so let's see if we can find the
eigenvectors
the eigenvectors
abstractly
are defined by x hat on psi of x
on psi
is equal to a number times psi
if we can find functions which satisfy
that those are the eigen functions or
the eigenvectors the eigenvectors of x
hat
what does it mean in terms of ordinary
functions
all it means let me erase this all it
means
is find the function psi of x
so that when you multiply it by x
you get
a multiple lambda of the original
function
now that looks a little absurd doesn't
it
a function such that when you multiply
it by x
just
gives you a number times the original
function
if you think about it for a minute
that's quite impossible well
it is impossible strictly speaking but
you can get very close to this so let me
show you what's involved
let's write this as x minus lambda
times psi of x equals zero
all i've done is transpose the right
hand side over to the left
x
minus the number lambda on psi of x is
equal to zero this should be thought of
as a
an equation for a function psi of x and
it must be true for all x when you write
a thing like this you mean that it
should be true for all x
well here's a product of two things
which has to be zero according to the
equation
what do i know if a product is equal to
zero
i know that at least that at least one
of the factors has to be equal to zero
yes we will assume that
we will assume that the integral of psi
star psi
always converges
we'll find out why in a little while
converges
in particular that means psi goes to
zero at large
whatever psi is
it should go to zero far away do
whatever it wants in here and then go to
zero nearby
the interpretation of that will become
clear in a little while
so it doesn't leak off to very very
large distances and get bigger and
bigger it goes to zero
assumption
fast enough to make this integral
converge
okay so let's take x minus lambda psi of
x equal to zero
what does this equation tell us it tells
us that anywheres where x is not equal
to lambda
here's lambda right over here x equals
lambda right over here
any place where x is not equal to lambda
psi has to be equal to zero
that means the only place where psi is
not zero
must be where x is equal to lambda
at x equal to lambda you can have psi
not equal to zero because at that point
x minus lambda is equal to zero
anywheres else
if this equation is to be true
psi has to be zero
so
let's plot
what psi has to look like
psi is a function which is zero
everywheres except that x equals lambda
as x equals lambda right there so it's 0
everywhere
except that there's one point where it
can be non-zero
now function like this is not a nice
continuous sensible function in
particular you can't square it and
integrate it a function which is only
non-zero at a single point
and so what dirac did was to invent
a kind of idealized
um j well a generalization of a function
the generalization of the function is
probably well known to most of you and
it's called the dirac delta function
at the moment i don't want to get deeply
into the mathematics i'm more interested
now in illustrating some of the concepts
that we've gone through
so let's imagine that what this really
means
is that it's a function which is
non-zero over a tiny tiny interval
in the end we'll allow that interval to
shrink to zero let's call the size of
that interval epsilon
epsilon for small number
epsilon
and the height of the function
will take to be one over epsilon
that's not in itself very important
at the moment
but just to put some area under that
function let's make the function as high
as it is narrow
that's a function which is zero
everywhere except in this tiny interval
near x equals lambda
it's a high narrow function which is
zero everywhere else
except in that tiny interval
that function is what dirac called the
delta function delta of x minus lambda
it's zero except when the argument is
equal to zero except when x minus lambda
is equal to zero
then the delta function is a high narrow
spike
but when x is not equal to zero or when
x minus lambda is not equal to zero the
function is zero
that's called the dirac delta function
now to give a precise mathematical
definition
you get uncomfortable with functions
which are as um
as loosely defined as this
and you should there is a precise
definition of the delta function we may
admit yeah
uh
that is yeah
when
yes
it's not orthonormal it's ortho but not
normal
the reason it's ortho let's let's see if
it's ortho first of all
ortho means well first of all let's
prove that this is an eigen well of
course it's an eigenvector of of x
it satisfies this equation x minus
lambda times psi of x is zero either
because psi is 0 or because x is equal
to lambda so yes it is an eigenvector
it's an eigenvector with eigenvalue
lambda but let's first ask about ortho
before normal ortho means that if i have
two different eigenvectors
with two different values of lambda
that they must be orthogonal to each
other so let's draw
another eigenvector corresponding to x
equals lambda prime
that's a function which looks like this
now as i said we will have to imagine in
the end that this epsilon shrinks to a
smaller and smaller size
but these two functions are orthogonal
to each other
because when you multiply them together
let's call phi and psi when you multiply
them together
one or the other is zero everywhere
when you multiply this by this
one or the other or both are zero
everywhere wherever this one is non-zero
this one is zero wherever this one is
non-zero this one is zero
so when you multiply them together you
always get zero
and therefore the inner product of them
is certainly zero
on the other hand
if you take
the eigenvector and take its inner
product with itself
you'll be squaring this high narrow
function
and the answer won't be zero
okay
so they're they're orthogonal to one
another
normalized will worry about another day
they're not uh they're not of unit norm
okay
this is an example
of an orthonor or sorry of a orthogonal
family of functions which are the
eigenvectors of the operator x
one eigenvector for each value of lambda
for each possible position
along the x-axis
now
in fact we've even found out what the
eigenvalues are
the eigenvalues are simply all the
possible values of x along the real axis
we could erect one of these delta
functions anywheres
any place we erected it will be an
eigenvalue or sorry an eigen
sometimes i use the word eigenfunction
eigenfunction is another word for
eigenvector
it's an eigenvector of the operator x
with eigenvalue lambda and lambda can be
anything on the real axis
so that's our
first example
of uh a
permission operator
a spectrum of eigenvalues spectrum just
means the collection of eigenvalues
orthogonality of the different
eigenvectors
and now let's uh discuss what a wave
function really means psi of x is called
the wave function
but uh let's
let's
discuss the following for simplicity i'm
going to take the height of this
function to be one over
the thickness of it and that means the
area under it is one
the area under a delta function is one
that's the definition of the delta
function
well let's take psi of x
and take its projection its inner
product
with the eigenvalue with the eigenvector
lambda
eigenvector lambda corresponds to a
particle located at position lambda
in other words it's the eigenvector
it's the eigenvector of the position and
it's the state in which the position has
a definite value
what is this inner product
this is the inner product
gotten by taking psi of x
and integrating it
with the wave function corresponding to
lambda but what is the wave function
corresponding to lambda
it's delta of x minus lambda
dx
this is the inner product of psi with
the eigenvalue lambda with the
eigenvector lambda
psi of x integrated with the eigenvector
this function is equal to something
special it's equal to something very
simple remember that psi of x is zero
everywhere except that x equals lambda
if it's zero everywhere is at x equals
lambda except x equals lambda it's only
sensitive to the value of psi
at x equals lambda
in other words over this whole tiny tiny
range here
the only values of psi which are
important
are the values of psi at x equals lambda
since the height of the function since
the area under the function is one
it's easy to prove okay here's here's
the argument
between this point and this point
psi doesn't vary very much assuming that
psi is nice and continuous
and if we take this interval
sufficiently small
psi will not vary very much across the
delta function
what is it right at the delta function
it's just equal to psi of lambda
so to a good approximation and a better
and better approximation as i shrink
this interval here
i can simply replace psi of x here by
psi at that one point psi of lambda
times delta of x minus lambda
integral
psi of lambda now can be brought outside
the integral
this doesn't depend on x anymore so we
bring it outside the integral and we
just have to integrate delta of x minus
lambda
the integral of delta of x minus lambda
is one
because i've defined the the the area
under the function to be one
so we just read off from this then that
this is just equal to psi of lambda
this is equal to psi of lambda
in other words
the wave function itself
psi of lambda or we could call it psi of
x we could replace
x by
x here
we can read this as saying the inner
product of psi
with a state which is localized at
position x
is just the wave function psi of x
that's what psi of x is it's just this
inner product
where this inner product now where i've
changed notation instead of calling the
eigenvalues lambda i've called them x
themselves now
this corresponds to a wave function
localized right at x
okay so where are we now
we now know mathematically
that psi of x is sort of just a
component of the vector psi
along the basis vectors
x
but now let's use the postulate what
have we done we've erased all the
postulates oh my goodness we
we've what was the fifth postulate
not euclid's fifth postulate but the
quantum fifth postulate
it was about probabilities it said that
the probability for getting a particular
lambda
is the square
of the vector
projected onto the eigenvector lambda
in this context it says the pr sorry
squared
in this context it says the probability
for detecting a particle
at position x
the probability to detect the particle
is just equal to
psi
x
quantity squared
or absolute value squared
but what is this psi x
it's just psi of x
times psi star of x
in other words we've now found out what
the meaning
of psi of x is
that it's the thing that you sc well
it's not the full meaning of it but a
partial meaning of it is it's the thing
whose absolute value squared is the
probability to detect the particle at x
so we've used the postulates of quantum
mechanics
to determine in terms of the wave
function
what the
what the probability to locate a
particle at x's
no i mean psi could be any old function
but for any old function there will be a
probability distribution
whatever psi is
and psi can be complex so i need not be
real
it can be negative in places
so psi is some complicated complex
function that can be negative positive
and imaginary and all those things
if you take it and multiply it by its
complex conjugate you'll get something
real and positive
that real positive thing
is the probability to find the particle
at different locations on the x-axis
that's the implication of the postulates
of quantum mechanics
in particular it says that probabilities
are given by the squares of certain
complex functions
now if all you get out of it was the
probability for uh for finding particles
in different places you might say why
the hell don't i just define the
probability as a function of x why do i
go through this complicated operation of
defining a complex function psi and then
squaring it
the reason is because there are other
things that you could measure besides
the position of the particle
there are other hermitian operators
which correspond to other observables
in particular
let's think about other possible
permission operators
i'm just going to give you another
simple one the simple one corresponds to
a very basic thing in quantum mechanics
i'll name it
as we go along
but before i name it let's just define
it in abstract operator sense
not abstract a concrete operator sense
again we're still doing the particle on
the line
it's states are described by functions
psi of x in other words it's
the vector space is again the functions
of x same exact setup as before
but now i'm going to think about a
different observable
a different observable which is
characterized by a different operator
the operator now is not multiplication
by x
multiplication by x
is what we did over here
now a different operation
differentiation
just differentiate psi of x
that's an operation
in fact it's a linear operator
if i differentiate
i can differentiate the sum of two
functions i can multiply the function by
a number if i multiply the function by a
number its derivative is just the
numerical number times the times the
derivative of the original function
i can add functions and differentiate
them
d by dx is a linear operator acting on
the space of function psi of x so this
is another operator
does it correspond to an observable not
quite
not quite because it's not hermitian
it's what's called anti-hermitian
anti-hermitian means all you have to do
is multiply it by i to get something
hermitian
but let's first prove that it's not
in fact
i'll prove that it's anti-hermitian let
me tell you what anti-hermitian means
i'll just define it right now
it's a class of operators that were
discovered by hermite's aunt
empty her mission he
all right anti-hermitian remember what
her mission means her mission means
that a
psi
b
is equal to the complex conjugate of b
oh what am i saying psi h excuse me h
h
a complex conjugated
that's the meaning of remission in
particular
it says that a
hey
i don't
and why not
don't i i think i do yeah
all right
anti-hermitian says that a h b
is equal to minus
b
h a
that's called anti-hermitian
if you spend five minutes you'll realize
that for every and oh this is
anti-hermitian let's call it uh h
what about the hat
operator
you mean this notation here yeah you
were splitting hairs but properly so um
i don't know where to do it i don't know
what to call it let's just call it uh
yeah yeah sorry star
it's exactly the same as hermitian but
an extra minus sign
it's very easy to prove that if you have
an anti-hermitian operator if you
multiply it by i it becomes hermitian
and the reason is because the complex
conjugate of i is minus i
if you have an anti-hermitian operator
and you multiply it by plus or minus i
let's say minus i
oh boy this looks like i doesn't it
okay
anti-hermitian
it's not a times h
it's anti-hermitian
if i take an anti-hermitian operator and
multiply it by i
i get a hermitian operator
that's a little theorem to prove do it
yourselves but it just follows from the
fact that the complex conjugate of i is
minus i so
uh no h-bar please not now you're
confusing me
okay but um in fact d by dx is
anti-hermitian but let's just see why it
is that um
uh that
d by dx is not hermitian and why you
discover an extra minus sign there
i'll tell you what let me let me cut it
short let me cut it short by simplifying
let me tell you right now that the thing
which is hermitian
is i times d by dx
in other words
or minus i doesn't matter i or minus i
minus i d by d x on psi of x is a or
minus i d by d x is an operation
it's a linear operator on the space of
functions
and it's a hermitian
linear operation
let's see if we can prove that let's see
if we can prove that it's hermitian the
simplest way to prove it
is to prove
that
let's call let's give it a name
i'm going to give it the name
k hat
i'm not going to call it h i'm going to
call it k but it's hermitian k hat on
psi of x
the simplest way to prove it is to prove
that for any psi
psi
k
is real
now that sounds a little odd because k
has an i in it it looks awfully much
like it's going to be imaginary
but it's not
let's check it
we have to calculate psi star
that's the left that's the bra vector
k hat is minus i d by dx
times
psi
or just
decide the x
now it doesn't look real but it is real
to prove that it's real
we want to prove that it's its own
complex conjugate
so let's prove that this thing is its
own complex conjugate and the way we
prove it is by integrating by parts
does everybody know how to integrate by
parts
integrate by parts is a very simple
thing
if you have the product of two functions
f of g
f
times
dg by dx and you integrate
the product of a function with the
derivative of another function
the answer is minus
g
times the derivative of f
you simply interchange which of them is
differentiated
instead of differentiating g we
differentiate f and you throw in an
extra minus sign
that's called integrating by parts it's
a standard elementary calculus
theorem
what am i missing out of this
the end points of the integration
but the argument for the end points is
that i've chosen functions psi which go
to zero far away if they go to zero far
away i don't have to worry about the end
points of the integration
so let's integrate this by parts
to integrate it by parts i simply throw
in another minus sign this must be equal
to
plus we have to change the sign plus i
times the integral and now i interchange
which of the which of the things gets
the uh gets the uh complex or gets the
derivative it becomes the psi star by dx
times psi
that's this
all right so i have this is equal to
this
integral psi star times minus i d psi by
dx is plus i
times integral d psi star by dx
now i assert that this the second term
the second expression the right hand
side is simply the complex conjugate of
the top
let's check that let's take the complex
conjugate of the right hand side of the
equation the complex conjugate of the
right hand side
first of all has the complex conjugate
of i
so let's i'm going to rewrite the
complex i'm going to write
i'm going to write the complex conjugate
of
i'm this
going to write equals just complex
conjugate here it is cc complex
conjugate
what's the complex conjugate of i
minus i
what's the complex conjugate of psi
psi star right
what's the complex conjugate of d psi
star by dx
decide the x
but look the complex conjugate of the
right hand side
is just the left hand side
minus i
psi star
d psi by dx
so what have i proved
i've proved that this is its own complex
conjugate
by integration by parts i prove that the
left side of the equation is equal to
the right side
but then i prove that the right side
here is just the complex conjugate of
the left side
no
yeah
so i prove that this is its own complex
conjugate
if it's its own complex conjugate it
means that it's real
and it means
that minus i d by dx is a hermitian
operator
right
the extra sign or this
it's a little surprising you might have
thought that just d by dx was hermitian
but it's not
okay
so minus i k which is
just minus i d by dx
is a hermitian operator
let's find out what its eigenvectors are
if it's a hermitian operator it must
have a lot of eigenvectors
let's see if we can find out what the
eigenvectors are and then see if we can
interpret them and figure out what
observable
what quantity that you can measure
this operator k corresponds to
okay
so
here's the eigenvalue equation let's
write the eigenvalue equation
minus i the psi by dx
should equal this is the action of
k
on side this is k on psi
k is minus id by dx
if it's to be if psi is to be an
eigenvector what does the right hand
what does the right side have to be
lambda times psi where lambda is the
eigenvalue
let's call the eigenvalue k
just to call it by its traditional name
let's call it little k
this corresponds to an eigenvalue
times psi of x
so we're looking for functions
the eigenvector functions are those
whose derivatives or minus i derivatives
are equal to k times psi of x itself
everybody know how to solve an equation
like this
anybody know how to solve an equation
exponentials
exponentials the solution of this
equation is that psi of x
is proportional to e to the i k x
okay let's check that
rather than solve it let's just check
that this is the solution of the
equations
e to the i k x of course means cosine k
kx
plus i sine kx
let's check that let's check that minus
i d by d psi by dx is k times psi
so to differentiate this every time you
differentiate it it pulls down
the coefficient i k so decide by the x
is equal to i k
times e to the ikx which is just i k
times psi
now i want minus i times this so let's
multiply by minus i
what's minus i times plus i
just one
so we find out that this function here
is an eigenvector of the operator minus
id by dx
okay so in fact
we have found the eigenvectors
of the operator minus id by dx
and they are simply the functions cosine
x plus i sine x
let's think about those functions for a
minute
those functions are very very different
than the eigenvectors of x the
eigenvectors of x or these
highly peaked delta functions
these functions here are spread all over
the map
the map meaning x they're spread all
over the map there are oscillations
which endlessly go on and on
cosine
looks like this
sine looks like
well
let me uh draw a sine in blue
yeah i can't i can't draw i sign though
but i can draw a sine i'm not saying
don't add don't add the blue to the
black
multiply the blue by i before you
before you add it to the black
but i can't draw that let's see
it starts here
and uh
and
it has the same wavelength i don't know
has the same wavelength but it's 90
degrees out of phase we know what sine
and cosine look like i'm not going to
try to draw them
all right this is the eigenfunctions and
it's got a plus i cosine kx plus i sine
kx
right what is the magnitude supposing i
multiply psi of x by its own complex
conjugate
what do i get
one the number one psi times psi star
is just one
e to the i k x times e to the minus i k
x
e to the minus i k x is the complex
conjugate of psi psi times psi star is
1.
remember
yes there's an ambiguous constant in
here all right but whatever that
constant is
psi star psi is constant that means that
the probability to find the particle
anywheres in space is uniform
complete uniform probability
distribution
there's no information in this where the
particle is
but
the function oscillates and those
oscillations must mean something
okay
let's see if we can figure out what they
mean by using uh
first of all um let me say this first of
all
according to the postulates
k corresponds to some kind of observable
its eigenvalues are
little k here just numbers any number
from minus infinity to plus infinity
will do will be an eigenvector will be
an eigenvalue
what are we to call this operator
well we've got to give it a name
to give it a name i'm going to relate
this to some
very primitive observations about
quantum theory
before real quantum mechanics was
discovered going back to einstein and
the broglie this is for the purpose of
giving it a name
yes yes yes you're entirely right
and uh in fact there are no
true eigenvectors of psi of x which go
to zero at infinity but you can find
you can find functions which are
arbitrarily close to this arbitrarily
close to solving this
by taking functions which oscillate and
then far away gradually diminishing in
magnitude you are right i don't want to
get into that now the normalization of
the functions but you are right and one
has to do a little bit of explanation
here about why i'm allowed to get away
with functions which don't go to zero at
infinity i didn't want to do that now i
want mostly i wanted to illustrate the
principles by
working out some examples of
eigenvectors eigenvalues and so forth so
allow me the freedom to ignore that
issue of whether the functions go to
zero for the moment
at least they don't blow up at least
they don't get big
and that is important
for the moment i want to find out i want
to name this observable if i name it i
mean i want some intuitive connection
with something that i already know
all right so the eigenfunctions the
eigenfunctions after all are the
wave functions which correspond to a
definite value
of this observable
what shall i call that observable
well first of all let's think about the
wavelength of these oscillations these
are waves
the wavelength
is this distance
the wavelength is the distance that
you'll have to move
before cosine kx comes back to itself
cosine k cosine 0 starts at one how far
do you have to move before cosine comes
back to one
well the answer is two pi
but it's not x equals two pi it's kx
equals two pi
right so the wavelength corresponds
to k times the wavelength l
is equal to 2 pi
or the wavelength here l
divided by k
so we could either characterize these
waves as having a certain value of k a
certain eigenvalue or we could
equivalently characterize them by
their wavelength and their wavelength is
l
right
now next
we make use of a intuition
which goes back to the broglie
and also to einstein
that
if we have particles corresponding to
waves
of a given wavelength
those particles have a certain momentum
now we're only using this to name a
certain thing
i cannot legitimately claim at this
point to explain to you why we're going
to call something momentum we will do
that later
in order to see that something is really
behaving like momentum we have to do a
lot more but for the moment i just want
to put you know sort of a um
uh
what should we call it
just throwing a bunch of stuff together
that that we've seen earlier in order to
give this thing a name a familiar name
all right what the broglie said
is that if we have a beam of particles
corresponding to a wave of wavelength l
that those particles have a momentum
and the momentum let's call the momentum
p it's the same term that we used in
classical physics
anybody remember what the broglie said
p is equal to
h over l
this is also the thing that heisenberg
used the shorter the wavelength
the higher the momentum of the
corresponding particles
and it's planck's constant h which goes
in there
so if you have a
set of photons for example
a set of photons which are described by
a classical wave of wavelength l
then what einstein knew in which he
didn't say but with the broglie
reinterpreted and generalized to any old
particles not just photons
is that the momentum of those particles
described by a given wave
is given by
h divided by l
well l is 2 pi over k so let's plug that
in
that says that this is h
and then we have to turn l over
so that's k
divided by 2 pi
h over 2 pi has another name it's called
h
bar so this is h-bar plunk's other
constant times ke
momentum
is h-bar times k
so we now have an interpretation it's an
interpretation that we're going to have
to check later when we understand the
connection between quantum mechanics and
classical mechanics
momentum is a classical concept
we're now using sort of seed of the
pants old style quantum mechanics
the intuitive confused ideas of uh that
were before heisenberg and schrodinger
but let's use them and justify them
later
that wavelength and momentum are
connected in a certain way whereas that
wavelength and momentum are connected in
a certain way and if i then plug in i
find that momentum is connected to k
momentum
is h-bar times k do i have that right
yes
momentum is h bar times k
well that now
interprets for us what the physical
meaning of the observable k is
it's just the momentum of a particle
except in units of h-bar
k is just the momentum of a particle in
units of h-bar
if you don't like calling it momentum
don't call it momentum just call it the
observable k
right
you can just call it the observable k
and you see that it's eigen
values and its eigen functions are just
the numbers k and the wave functions e
to the i k x
the interesting point here is that
whatever k is it is of course it is of
course the momentum but whatever k is
the eigenvectors of it are completely
different than the eigenvectors of the
position x
the eigenvectors of the position x are
these high narrow functions which are
also
slightly ill-defined
and the eigen functions of momentum are
these functions which oscillate on and
on forever and ever and have a
completely uniform probability
distribution
in each case there's something
mathematically a little wrong
in one case
this is clearly a thing which needs a
better mathematical definition and in
the other case
we are allowing functions now which
don't go to zero and infinity these two
things are related but
without being
too precise and without being too uh
mathematically rigorous
we now see that whatever these objects
are whatever these wave functions are
they're completely different for
position and momentum in particular
no eigenfunction of position
is also an eigenfunction of momentum
well that sounds familiar
it sounds something like the uncertainty
principle if the eigenfunctions of
position are the states in which if you
measured the position you would know
exactly what it was
and if the eigenfunctions of momentum
are the wave functions
which correspond to a definite value of
momentum
it's quite clear that they sort of clash
with each other
if you know
the position of a particle that's
equivalent to saying that you know that
its wave function is peaked like that
if you know the momentum of a particle
it means that the wave function is
spread out all over the place
it can't be both and that of course is
the source of the uncertainty principle
which we don't have we're not going to
do tonight
but it's the source of it
and it's an example of incompatible
quantities
quantities which correspond another way
to say it
is if you think
of the eigenfunctions of position is
forming a basis of vectors
in a very high dimensional vector space
but i'm going to draw it as just
three-dimensional
then the eigenfunctions of momentum
are simply different
eigenvectors pointing in
different directions so that no
eigenfunction of position is also an
eigenfunction of momentum and no
eigenfunction of momentum is an
eigenfunction of position
they correspond to different basis sets
which are at angles relative to each
other
uh
we've now
kind of gone through one example
of a space
of a vector space the space of functions
of x
and the interpretation of a couple of
different
linear operators
the linear operator corresponding to
position and the linear operator
corresponding to momentum
what would we really have to do to see
that
it's more or less clear
intuitively
that a wave function which is peaked at
a location in space corresponds to a
particle at that location of space
what would we really want to do in order
to see that
that this other observable
really does correspond to the momentum
of a particle well momentum is a
classical concept
and in order to understand in what sense
this thing corresponds to momentum
we have to be able to understand the
limit of quantum mechanics
in which it behaves like classical
mechanics
it's quite obvious that there must be
such a limit
if quantum mechanics governs everything
it governs electrons it also governs
bowling balls
but bowling balls are very heavy and
they correspond to a limit of quantum
mechanics a limit of quantum mechanics
of heavy objects
what we would have to do in order to see
that this object that i've called
momentum really behaves like classical
momentum is to understand that limit
better
and we will we'll come back to that
limit
for the moment
calling k momentum or calling h bar
times k momentum is just a name
it's just a name for an object named for
an observable
okay any questions yes
i have a comment right
the the psi of x
equals
i agree
so let me say
um good so let me let me uh just uh
restate what you just said
more uh
completely
the complex number e to the ikx
is a number whose magnitude is one e to
the i k x times e to the minus i k x is
one which means that it's a number in
the complex plane which lies on the unit
circle
okay
and of course it's equal to
cosine
of something cosine kx plus i sine kx
now if i imagine
the complex plane
being oriented this way
and the x-axis oh this is different x
sorry this is uh
psi psi
psi is a point on the complex plane
and if it has if it's of the form e to
the i k x that means it's on the unit
circle here
psi is on the unit circle
this would be the real part of psi
real part of psi
in this direction and the imaginary part
of psi in that direction let's not
confuse x and y with the position of the
particle
now supposing i draw the complex plane
this way
remember the wave function is a complex
function
and the x-axis the position of the
particle that way
that means that at every point of space
i could draw the complex plane
and plot psi as a point
on the complex plane at every x
so at every x
psi
is a point on the complex plane and in
fact for this kind of function
it's a point on the unit circle
so as was pointed out what it
corresponds to
is a point which as you move along
winds around like a helix
winds around on the unit circle like a
helix
that may help some people it helps me
small k means very long wavelength means
it winds slowly
small k means large wavelength
right
large k is small wavelength so large k
means that it varies very very quickly
right so large k means it winds very
quickly as we move along
small k means that it winds very slowly
as we move along
right
yeah that's that's a good point
uh any other questions or comments some
of the comments are helpful so
on your possibilities you didn't say
anything about like quantum collapse
no not at this point not yet
not yet not yet um one other point
one of the points that we haven't talked
about which we'll talk about next time
we have not talked about the probability
for different momentums we talked about
the probability for different positions
it was just psi star of x i of x
we have not talked about the probability
for different momenta
all right so we'll talk about that next
time a little bit
and uh right we have not talked about
basically i've not talked about the
measurement process itself
and what it does to the system the
actual active measurement we only said
the probability for a given measurement
is given by this or that
big k is small l and big l and vice
versa
that's what we just said
no we didn't
we said
small k corresponds to slow variation
which means big l
large k corresponds to rapid oscillation
which means smaller
well okay
momentum
we usually think of as having to do with
dx by dt
right
what we do all right so let me let me
state it for you then there's an
approximation to quantum mechanics which
is good for heavy particles and heavy
objects and in that approximation
the wave function
moves around tends to form a lump
and this lump moves around what we're
going to want to prove is that this lump
moves around in more or less the in
accord with the classical equations of
motion
and we're going to want to prove
that the velocity that it moves around
with
is related to how fast the wave function
is varying
so if we have a wave function which
varies quickly like that
so that it corresponds to a large k
we're going to want to discover that it
moves across the blackboard faster as if
it was a high momentum particle
but to do that we have to understand how
things change with time
we haven't even brought time into it yet
so the correspondence between momentum
and what we normally call classical
momentum
is through the question of how wave
packets move around
we're going to want to see that wave
packets move around in a chord with
pretty much the classical equations of
motion
good
any other questions
got one more minute
before i collapse
before my wave function collapses
you know how many hours i've been
teaching today
for
well my father used to work 18 hours a
day but you know
but
you're supposed to feel sorry for me
now the preceding program is copyrighted
by stanford university please visit us
at stanford.edu